Sophie Treadwell papers, 1905-1969
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Sophie Treadwell, 1905-1969
MS 124
Treadwell, Sophie, 1890-1970
Collection of typescript manuscripts, both published and unpublished; chiefly plays, but also novels, articles, stories, and television scripts. Several versions of each play are present. Also included is correspondence, copyrights, lectures, clippings, photographs of Treadwell, and travel diaries.
11.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
American journalist, playwright, and author.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series.
Series I: Correspondence and Miscellaneous Items, 1928-1969
Series II: Plays, 1905-1967
Series III: Novels and Other Writings, 1906-1968
Scope and Content Note
Collection of typescript manuscripts, both published and unpublished; chiefly plays, but also novels, articles, stories, and television scripts. Several versions of each play are present. Also included is correspondence, copyrights, lectures, clippings, photographs of Treadwell, and travel diaries. Correspondents include friends, literary agents, producers, actors, actresses, and scene designers. Ephemera consists of travel brochures, postcards, a few watercolors, and two etchings of Austrian buildings.
Most of the manuscripts in this collection were undated. Whenever a copyright date could be located, it was used, even though the particular play or novel might obviously have been written several years earlier.
In general, correspondence - including that with producer Arthur Hopkins - has been place with related manuscripts whenever possible. Exceptions have been made in the case of the various literary agents who handled a variety of scripts, and in the segregation of extensive correspondence with certain individuals. Files in Box 1 have many references to separately-boxed plays and novels.
Most materials are English with a small amount in Spanish and German.
Access Terms
Treadwell, Sophie, 1885-1970 -- Archives
Theater -- United States -- 20th century -- Sources
Actors -- United States -- Correspondence
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Sources
Manuscripts, American
Drama -- 20th century -- Stories, plots, etc. -- Sources
Women dramatists, American -- Sources
Television plays, American -- Sources
Correspondence
Dialogues
Manuscripts
Photographs
Diaries
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence and Miscellaneous Items, 1928-1969
  - Correspondence; Copyright, 1928-1969
    - Correspondence: Lawyer M. L. Malevinsky (regarding various plays; for legal matters, see following file). 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Agent Adrienne Morrison, Pinker & Son. 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Agent Miriam Howell. 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Agent Helen Harvey. 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Agent Phyllis Anderson. 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Agent John Gibbs Agency. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Agent Leah Salisbury. 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Agent Lucy Kroll. 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: Terese Hayden. 1943, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Zita Johann. 1928-1937? (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Robert Edmond Jones. 1937-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Alexander Koiransky. 1928?-1953? (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: Abby Mann, etc. 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: Donald Oenslager. 1937-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Lawrence Langner, Theresa Helburn, Theatre Guild. (Includes correspondence regarding television versions of various plays). 1945, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: Wisconsin Center for Theatre Research. 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: Miscellaneous. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: Book Orders and Subscriptions. 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence: Property in California. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: Property in California, "The Beverly Dream." 1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Copyrights. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Articles, Trips, Miscellaneous, 1924-1949
    - Miscellaneous Personal Items, including Photographs. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Articles on Mexico for New York Herald Tribune. 1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Articles on Mexico for New York Herald Tribune. 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Articles on Mexico for New York Herald Tribune. 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mexico (Miscellaneous Material). (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Mexico (Miscellaneous Publications). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "The Log of a Chrysler." (Automobile trips in Europe, U. S. and Mexico). 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Far East Trip. (Diary, Notes, etc.). 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Far East Trip. (Travel Brochures, etc.: India, Egypt, Ceylon). 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Far East Trip. (Travel Brochures, etc.: China, Japan). 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notes on Modjeska. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lectures for Koiranski. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Russian Theory of Acting. (Notes, clippings). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Personal Interest Clippings. (Topics as listed by Sophie Treadwell), 1964, no date
    - Architecture. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Books. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Crime. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Man. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Morals. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Movies. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - The Negro. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - People. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Philosophy and Religion. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Poems. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Politics. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Schools. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Theatre. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Tucson, Arizona. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - U.S.A. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Woman. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Zoology. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Wien. 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - World Affairs. (Including Nazism, Russia, Isolation, Lindberg). (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Notes on Sutter. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Early Manuscripts; etc., 1906, no date
    - University of California Notebooks. (Poetry, Miscellaneous fragments, etc.). 1906 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Plays: untitled, unfinished, fragments. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Story: "Letters from 'A' to 'B'." (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Stories: various. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Notes, clippings, etc. on K. Jaspers, Monakow, and psychology. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series II: Plays, 1905-1967
  - Plays: Early, 1905-1918
    - Le Grand Prix. ("my first play"). ca. 1905 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Constance Darrow. 1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Right Man. 1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Settlement. (4 versions; also called Limelight). 1911 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Madame Bluff. 1918 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - The Answer. 1918? (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - One-act Play: Trance. 1918 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - One-act Plays. (Box 5, Folder 9)
      La Cachucha
      Guess Again
      His Luck
      John Doane
      A Man's Own
      Mrs. Wayne (later titled The Eye of the Beholder)
      Sympathy (the first Sophie Treadwell play produced)
      To Him Who Waits
  - Plays: Edgar Allen Poe, 1919-1962
    - Poe (4 acts, 6 scenes, 2 versions). (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Nepenthe (4 acts, 5 scenes). (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Poe (3 acts, 5 scenes). (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Edgar Allen Poe (3 acts, 5 scenes, 2 versions). (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Plumes in the Dust (3 acts, 6 scenes). (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (includes John Barrymore, Guthrie McClintic, Eugene O'Neill, Kenneth Macgowan). 1919-1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Plays: Rights and Gringo, 1921-1941
    - Rights and later versions with titles, The King Passes, Mary Beaton, Love and Principle, Rights. 1921, 1938, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Gringo (various versions). 1922 (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
    - Gringo (correspondence, box office statements, etc.). 1922-1923, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Plays: Various, 1918-1925
    - Philomel (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Loney Lee (later version of Philomel). 1923 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - O' Nightingale (later version of Loney Lee). 1923 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Laughter (a play about Chaplin's youth). 1922? (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Claws. 1918 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Old Rose (later version of Claws). 1921 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Love Lady (later version of Old Rose). 1924 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - You Can't Have Everything (2 versions). 1925 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - Many Mansions (2 versions). 1925 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Play: Lone Valley, 1926-1933
    - Inheritance (1st version of Lone Valley). (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Better to Marry (2nd and 3rd versions). (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - Deliverance (4th version). (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Wild Honey (5th version). (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Set Free (6th version). (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Bound (7th version). (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Lone Valley (8th, 9th & 10th versions) (Box 9, Folder 8-10)
    - Correspondence, etc., (includes letter from Katherine Hepburn). (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Play: Machinal, 1928-1964
    - Correspondence. 1928-1964 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (foreign rights and productions). 1928-1963 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Clippings and Miscellaneous Items. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Play: Machinal, 1928-1961
    - Various versions, including the 1961 production in New York. (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
  - Plays: Ladies Leave and Million Dollar Gate, 1929-1930
    - Ladies Leave (2 versions). 1929 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Million Dollar Gate (4 versions). 1930 (Box 12, Folder 2-5)
  - Plays: For Saxophone, 1934
    - Various versions. (Box 13, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - German version. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Plays: Various, 1930-1936
    - The Island (3 versions). 1930 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Andrew Well's Lady. 1931 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - The Last Are First (1st version of Promised Land, includes letter from Thomas Mitchell). 1933 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Promised Land (2 versions, includes letters from Paul Muni and Theresa Helburn). 1933? (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Three (2 versions). 1936 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - Play: Hope for a Harvest, 1938-1953
    - Correspondence (includes letters from Frederic March, Theresa Helburn, Lawrence Langner). 1941-1953 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Contracts, Sketches, etc. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Notes during re-write. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Box office statements. 1941 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Clippings. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Source material. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Various versions. no date (Box 15, Folder 7-10)
  - Play: Hope for a Harvest, 1938-1941
    - Various dated and/or indentified versions. 1938-1941 (Box 16, Folder 1-9)
  - Play: Highway, 1942-1955
    - Correspondence (includes letters from Margaret Webster, Lawrence Langner, Howard Lindsay, Theresa Helburn, Marc Connelly, Eliott Nugent). 1942-1955 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Various versions (including television scripts). (Box 17, Folder 2-9)
  - Play: The Last Border, 1943-1946
    - Correspondence (includes letters from Florence Eldridge, Katharine Cornell, Margaret Webster, Alfred Lunt, Helen Hayes, Lawrence Langner). 1943-1946 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Various versions with changing titles: Madrid 7, The Watched Door, Borderline, The Last Border. 1945-1946 (Box 18, Folder 2-12)
  - Plays: The Last Border and A String of Pearls, 1943-1953
    - The Last Border (various versions). 1947 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
    - The Last Border (German version). (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - A String of Pearls: Correspondence. 1951-1953 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - A String of Pearls (various versions). 1943?-1950 (Box 19, Folder 6-10)
  - Plays: Judgement in the Morning, Garry, The Siren, 1951-1954
    - Judgement in the Morning: Correspondence (includes letters from Louis Calhern, Alfred Lunt, Billy Rose, Theresa Helburn). 1951-1954 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Judgement in the Morning (various versions, with changing titles: Don't Leave Me, I was Like That in a Way, I was Like That, Judgement in the Morning). 1952 (Box 20, Folder 2-7)
    - In Loving Lost (early version of Garry). (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Garry (also version as cut for television). 1954 (Box 20, Folder 9-10)
    - The Siren. 1953 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Play: Woman With Lilies, 1948-1968
    - Correspondence. 1956-1968 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Background, notes, etc. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Sauce for the Goose (early version of Woman With Lilies). (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Take My Ear (early version of Woman With Lilies). 1950 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Siempre (early version of Woman With Lilies). 1954 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Woman With Lilies (3 undated versions, including one identifiedas "original version for U. A." - University of Arizona). (Box 21, Folder 6-8)
  - Play: Woman With Lilies, 1967
    - Now He Doesn't Want to Play (3 versions, including copy of Peter Marroney's copy as performed in Tucson, Arizona, July 26-29, 1967). (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - Woman With Lilies (copy made after "the Tucson debacle"). (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Woman With Lilies (last version). December 15, 1967 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Woman With Lilies (various endings, fragments, re-writes). (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Series III: Novels and Other Writings, 1906-1968
  - Novels: Lusita and Hope for a Harvest, 1930s-1948
    - Lusita. 1930s (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Hope for a Harvest: Correspondence. 1939-1948 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Hope for a Harvest (fragments, "pages from original"). (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Hope for a Harvest (2 incomplete versions). (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
    - Hope for a Harvest (final typescript). (Box 23)
  - Novel: One Fierce Hour and Sweet, 1957-1964
    - One Fierce Hour and Sweet: Correspondence. 1957-1964 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - One Fierce Hour and Sweet (3 versions, including 2 with first title: Deep Well Center). (Box 24, Folder 2-4)
    - One Fierce Hour and Sweet: Reviews. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Novels: By Line and The Great Name Story, 1959-1966
    - Outlines only. (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
    - The Great Name Story: Correspondence. 1959-1966 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - The Hill and the Bay (fragments of an early version of The Great Name Story). 1961? (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
    - The Great Name Story (chapters 1-47 of the Abbott Magness version, also some fragments). 1965? (Box 25, Folder 6-9)
  - Novel: The Great Name Story, 1968?
    - The Great Name Story (2nd version, chapter 1-26). (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    - The Great Name Story (Anna Magness version, miscellaneous notes, outlines beginning chapters, etc.). 1968? (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1919-1948
    - Work for United Artists: New York Nights and Blind Raftery. 1929 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Play: Actress (incomplete). (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Play: Untitled (outline and notes only, folder is marked "San Salvador"). (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Television Dramas: The Gorgeous Innocent and Natalie, Inc. (also titled Women are Terrible). (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Novel: Rio Bravo (incomplete). (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Novel: About a young girl in New York and Mexico (incomplete). (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Story: "Heaven on Earth." 1948 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Early Scenarios: (Box 27, Folder 8)
      Deep Waters
      Mora
      Laurite
      Sauce and the Goose
      Mother Lode
      Tracks' End
    - Scenarios with William High. (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Bill and a Hatbox (2-part story published in Live Stories, August and September, 1919)
      The Career of Liltha Zane (a synopsis).
      Joan's Job (a synopsis).
    - Collaborations with Gilda (unidentified). (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous stories, "ideas," and fragments. (Box 27, Folder 11)